we've got some more sessions now, between now and lunchtime.
And the first one, I think has got one of the most tantalizing descriptions.
Paul Stack.
I scrolled down and it says, we'll cover why we made the decision
to stop writing code. I'm just going to stop there.
I think that sounds excellent.
Let's all just stop writing code.
I love that idea.
For those of you who were here earlier where it was really,
really busy, we've got some more chairs we're going to bring in at lunchtime.
So when it gets busy later, there'll be plenty of places to sit.
Do not worry, but I'll hand over right now,
because Paul is here to talk about why he stops writing code.
Thanks, Paul.
For the people on the live stream, the room is absolutely packed.
It's not. Don't listen to what I say. I'm joking. I'm kidding.
Okay, so my name is Paul Stack.
I am here to talk about that.
If humans architect the system, then the AI writes the code.
I want to I want you to give me 25 minutes.
That's all.
And I'm going to show you why.
It doesn't matter about code anymore.
Code is not actually the thing.
And just before I kicked, I joined the stage.
I kicked off a process which is our process of how
we actually author systems within our company.
And I'll show you the output at the end.
So we do not write any single code, okay.
Not a single line of code have I written since, I don't know, maybe
end of end of January. This is how we work.
This is how I work.
I'm not here telling you this is how you should work.
Trust me, it's very liberating when you don't need to care about the code anymore.
But I promise
you is like a very interesting direction and a very interesting way of going.
I'm going to show you our process in detail, and you can take what's useful.
Everything I'm going to show you is open source.
You can play around with it. You can have a look at it.
You can see what craziness is in there.
But by the end of it, I want you to think through
like the types of things you can do. Okay.
The distinction here is between right
and code and building the machine that writes the code.
Okay. And the AI era.
That's the very interesting thing.
We hear about software
factories, 'dark software factories', all these different things.
It all boils down to a very similar thing in a very similar process.
So what we're going to cover here today is why do we stop writing code.
Okay. What changed when we did?
How do we decide guidelines. What is our architecture?
First pattern means how swamp.
I'll talk to you a little bit later about that crazy name, and how AI gives
you back the work that we actually got into the industry to go for here.
So the bottleneck is no longer thinking in software.
Okay?
It used to be that we had to think about, you know, how we took an idea,
how we push that idea through to users, how we tested that hypothesis.
And the timescale to do that was a huge amount of investment,
and we had to sink a lot of upfront thought and process into it.
Okay.
At the company I work at previously, it was called System Initiative.
Just last week we spun up a brand new company
based on the back of this, and it's called Elder Swamp Club.
At System Initiative.
We meant we spent six years building a product.
We're trying to revolutionize infrastructure as code
and the ways through infrastructure as code.
It was the most beautifully and I really mean it,
the most beautifully architected rust code base that you've ever seen.
Okay.
It was an incredibly well designed, distributed system
that ran many microservices that talk to each other
through event busses and did a lot of stuff.
And the January, we threw every single line of it away, every single line.
And it's not because
the code was bad, it's because the product we needed to rethink for the agenda era,
the product wasn't going to resonate as we went into AI and pushed forward.
Now we let unfortunately, we let the team go at that time
and five of us stayed behind.
Five of the whole company stayed behind.
And on January the 25th,
we started with a miro board
with not a single line of code written and the entire system.
We were like, right, let's redesign something from scratch and think through
what we actually did.
This slide I originally first gave this talk two months ago,
and I said two months, absolutely thrilled by what we have for months.
I'm blown away by what we've built.
Okay.
And I genuinely mean not not because I've built it,
but because I've actually built the product
that I've always wanted to work with as an operations person.
Yes, I am an ops person, a developer.
I've been writing code for a long period of time, and so I have a very
big interest in what we're actually trying to build here.
I worked at HashiCorp, build in Terraform, I worked at Plume Build and Plume.
I've worked in the developer tools base for a while,
so I'm incredibly opinionated, incredibly opinionated.
So for me, it's like very important to build something that I really care about.
So the question
is, if I'm not writing the code,
what am I doing instead?
Actually, it's even better.
Okay, I fell out of love with code maybe two years ago,
and the reason I fell out of love of code is because I was on a zoom call
with five other people, and they were talking about the naming
conventions of Nats, cuz, and I just, I wanted to, like, lose my mind.
Okay.
Least interesting thing in the world for me personally,
the people I was on the call with loved it.
They were so intrigued by it.
They really wanted it to be perfect.
I didn't care, okay, I just want to point out something.
I'm from Northern Ireland.
If I swear it just happens, it just I don't even realize it just slips out.
So I apologize in advance.
Okay, so for me now, what I actually do is even though I own the product
because I'm like actually like the person responsible for it,
but I actually only architecture that goes with the product.
I care about the design decisions, the constraints, the invariants,
the things that sort of make this system coherent for a user across time.
The engineers are getting consistently good output
when they
actually express what they want architecturally.
I wrote a blog post about this maybe
three weeks ago called the Vibes Don't Scale.
Okay?
It doesn't.
Okay, TLDR the blog post they don't scale.
Okay?
If you're Vicodin and there's no idea of what you're trying to do
and you give it a single line prompt, you're going to get somewhere.
Is it going to be the most secure, the most useful tool over time?
Probably not.
You're going to have to invest some serious time,
and you're probably spending a lot of tokens in order to do it.
So for us, we try and make them specific, unambiguous constraints,
which means we bond handwritten code.
Absolutely bond it.
We cannot.
None of us as engineers or people that work in the company,
we can't send a pull request when it's written by us.
It'll be it'll be deleted, removed, won't even be closed.
It'll be literally just deleted as a pull request.
It's not a guideline. It's not a preference.
It is literally how we do things.
Agents write every single line of code.
Okay, you can go to our repo.
Even though agents write the code, I promise you it's not awful.
I would like to say it's great. It's not.
I mean, there's going to be things that you'll look at and go, I don't like that.
I don't like how that's laid out.
That's taste.
Okay.
That's, you know, that's the least important part of it.
Naming conventions.
How many times have we argued
on pull requests, a software engineers over naming conventions,
and how many lines should a class have before it's refactored?
I once heard a ridiculous, absolutely ridiculous conversation
where somebody says,
if a class is over 100 lines, it should go into its own microservice.
I'm like, come on, this is this is stupid.
This is absolutely crazy.
Okay, so for us, it's much more about the fact that we give the LMS our agents,
very strict operational and design guidelines.
Okay.
That's what we work on on a day to day basis.
We work in the system design.
We work on the constraints that the agent has to work within.
We work with all of the pieces that the agent has to form really strict
guardrails about.
These are the patterns, the boundaries, the architectural constraints,
you know, the invariants that we must hold, things that have failed in the past
where you need to feed that data back in
so the agent doesn't make that same mistake again, because you know what?
Agents are bad.
They will make mistakes.
Actually, they'll tell you they haven't made a mistake,
but they absolutely have made mistakes.
So this is not for us documentation.
This is actually executable constraints.
And this is what's really really important.
Okay.
Also because we don't write code
we don't accept anybody else's code.
We are an open source tool.
We'll talk about that a little later.
I believe truly that the norms of open source are not changing in an AI world.
So many projects are being overwhelmed by AI driven tools,
by AI driven code that is going into the system,
and they're just not willing to maintain it.
So many people have built tools around this in order to stop it from happening.
Mitchell Hashimoto created a tool called voyage,
okay, where you actually have to watch and say that you're
not an agent and that you actually, you know, you're the right person.
That's like said in the code,
we don't accept any pull request at any way, shape or form.
And it's not because I don't trust your code.
I absolutely do not.
But what I'm trying to do
is I am trying to maintain the integrity of our supply chain.
Okay, I have end users of a binary.
The last thing I want to do is to try and open an attack surface,
where somebody who is inevitably smarter than me
will be able to inject code into the system.
And you see so many of these problems happening all over the internet today.
Okay.
Trivy got absolutely destroyed.
A couple of months ago.
We saw a mini Shai Hulud attack last week where 364
npm packages are actually at risk in the system.
So, you know, we're very much a case of AI will generate
really plausible well formatted test at code at scale.
And if we have to author and look at that code,
we're never going to be able to distinguish what is a supply chain
attack versus what is actually a change in the code itself.
So we just found it.
Okay.
I'm sure we got a lot of pushback from people.
They're like, oh, you know that that doesn't really seem great.
I absolutely will accept you
like drive in our product forward, give me issues, give me feature requests,
give me design specifications that you think are more interesting.
Give me where the code is not great and the system will actually
help drive it forward.
So for
us we have a full flow from idea
to merged code, and our flow looks kind of like this.
Okay, so we have a start a new triage an issue.
Okay.
We actually wrote, funnily enough, we're in an AI world.
We wrote a skill okay?
Everyone is writing skills.
Our skill is backed by a CLI. Okay.
Our skill, like our skill is,
is just guardrails running like the correct CLI tools to do it.
But effectively what's happening here is we triage an issue or a feature request.
It then gets classified.
It then goes into a loop of plan generated, review plan
generated, review plan generated review.
And that's an adversarial review okay.
So it's great that a plan, you know, an agent will say
this is the best plan for what you do.
Then I have written I have written a very grumpy,
adversarial review that says you don't trust any code in the world.
You have to prove that it's secure.
You have to prove that it has no injection attacks.
You have to prove that it is architecturally complete.
As to the guidelines.
And these two agents basically go into this loop
to figure out when it gets to the right thing.
We get to five, okay?
We'll only ever allow
five loops before it steps in and says, hey, we can't agree on this.
You have to be the arbiter of what's going on at that point.
I have to step in. Human is in the loop now.
At this point in time, plan is generated, plan is secure based on an adversarial
human has to say this is the right feature.
This is the right bug fix.
Here are the reasons why we then start
implementing it after an implementation we recreate it.
If it's a bug, we try and verify it.
If it's a feature, then it goes into pull request open.
Pull request open goes through another set of reviews.
If it's failed, then it goes back into implement it and so on and so forth.
Then we go into notify or excuse me, release it, and then we notify
the users who requested and we are done.
Okay.
This isn't a whole pile of shell scripts because that would be horrible
to maintain.
This is actually basically a state machine inside a skill and a CLI.
Incredibly simple, but actually incredibly powerful
because I can extend the state machine at any way, shape or form for us.
The entire entry point of the system is our MD.
Yes, we are cloud code users.
Okay, agents MD, you can swap in and you can do the same thing for us.
It's cloud code okay.
It is the executable contract.
It is literally the center of gravity in our entire system.
And therefore every cloud code or CI session will read
that claw code by default.
Now our cloud code is slightly different.
We don't like embed all like words.
We're not good with words. We're software engineers.
We have things like this okay TypeScript.
That must be strict.
No knees. Because knees are the devil.
It must be named exports. No default.
It has to be agPL copyright on the top of every file.
No fire and forget promises.
Don't lose people's memory.
Right then. Architecture.
Everything has to have log and Jason endpoints.
Everything has to import from mods.
You should never leak internal paths because that's an implementation detail.
These are the types of constraints that we care about okay?
These are the types of things that are very very important.
And then there's always a line at the bottom of our cloud code
that basically says, hey, if you hit a non-obvious problem
during a session that is going to trip up future users, future Claude
Sessions, Future agent sessions, record it and propose an update to your
MD before we continue.
So when we go in, then we go into a complete test and strategy.
We have unit test,
integration test, contract test, property test, architectural test.
And that's the end of the binary.
Once the binary is built,
we then take that, build binary and we ship it across to a different repo.
We take it completely out of the context of everything else
and we run it as a user. We run effectively.
Old UAT tests run this script.
Here is the intent of what it's going to do.
Run this command.
Here is what it's going to produce.
Never like hard coded for words.
That would be crazy.
And then we have another set of tests to sit on top.
Adversarial tests okay.
Those tests are try and inject it.
Try and kill the process in the middle.
Try and kill the data. Try and remove it.
Try and do everything that a user will ultimately do.
Not by mistake.
They just do it. And that's just what happens.
A user is your best user, your best QA of your entire system.
We try and treat those bugs that come in and we feed them
back into the adversarial.
Then our CI takes over.
CI for us actually has five marriage gates.
Okay, we have our code review because we need a code review.
That's just the way it works.
But then we have an adversarial review.
Assume everything is broken.
Try and prove that it's broken.
Then we have a user experience review.
Check the CLA.
Make sure that it doesn't regress the open.
Make sure that the commands of the correct structure.
We try and go known verb.
So we try and keep that sort of thing, create thing, get, etc. etc.
so we try and ensure that consistency and we have to encode that as a review step.
Then of course we need a CI
security review because all sorts of cheeky people,
they're going to be trying to inject stuff into my CI pipeline.
So I want to catch it before it even starts.
And then the last one, which is amazing considering
where we are and everything Guy said is for us, skill
checks are incredibly important, okay, not just the actual skill,
but the content, the format, the layout, the triggers.
That is a hard gate for us.
Our system is incredibly set up to be driven via an agent,
so therefore the agent experience must be really good.
So we literally will block any regressions
in content or experience as we go through.
When everything passes, it merges itself.
I'm not kidding.
Okay. The reason I'm not kidding is
if I show you
this pull request merged just before
I got in the stage.
And you can see the pull request was opened by my agent.
It had the first review,
then this one passed.
Then it goes a big old block and review.
I can't do that.
Agent then figured out that it had to push some changes.
Right here.
Keeps going.
This is all context. It's incredibly important.
There's the new change on the agent was actually able to go
and reproduce itself, figure out that everything was fine.
These suggestions are all okay.
And then it auto merged itself and kicked in okay.
We're not doing anything like out of the ordinary here.
We're just trusting a process that we continually hone in that process.
So for us, the gate is our UAT.
Just because someone has measures doesn't mean it
automatically gets to an end user.
We have this whole level of test that that goes through,
and we catch regressions every single day before it goes to end users.
Absolutely every single day. And it blocks our pipeline.
And nobody else can, like, publish a release out there until that's fixed.
Now the most important thing is here is in our UAT repo,
we have a line that says the tests are the source of truth.
Don't change the tests.
Always figure out if it's a regression in the binary.
Okay?
And what we've ended up with in the last 30 days is 295 issues have been opened.
And that's issues.
Not just bugs, but feature requests, etc.
I shipped 217 of them.
I closed 81 as either duplicates or just not things that we're going to do.
The median time to triage that's this is not work hours.
This is like elapsed hours in a day is 4.6 hours.
And from triage
the whole way through to ship, including all of those gates is 1.6 Ayers.
Okay. There's five people.
The company I work at, each of us has a closed code, Max Pro,
which is $200, and then we spend about 1500 to $2000 per month.
On the whole CI review process.
We're able to ship software many times faster now
for $3,000 per month than we were ever able to do before.
It's really not that, but what we've actually managed to do
is we've taught the system to debug itself.
Okay, so swamp actually knows when it encounters an error.
It will check the source control of the code out
at the version that it has the error at.
It will try and reproduce the error, and then it will open an issue on your behalf.
It will even check
if the issue has been fixed in a later version before it happens.
So we're trying to include this guardrail in and what we're doing.
And we end up with this like like really tight loop with bugs,
which means the bugs that we get from the agent are incredibly well formed,
and they have a lot of great context that goes with them.
So for us, we're not really just automating code.
We're actually building
the whole system that keeps the system running and keeps it going.
And what we care about here is we don't need a bus factor anymore.
We all work in teams where one person is like the overarching
architecture person who, you know, you need to go to ask
about the part of the system
that hasn't been changed every six months or every year.
Okay, we do an infrastructure as code.
We do it in platform.
We do it in actual software all the time.
Okay, we're trying to remove that bus factor
because we're trying to make the agent aware of the system.
An agent is in a fresh context every single time.
In the past, I don't even know how long, maybe
two months, I've not had to run slash clear in my context window.
Okay, because every report is a brand new clawed
work tree, which keeps it very focused, very specific,
and it means that it actually cares just about the context in that area.
So how can you get started?
Because that's the whole point of why we're at a conference like this.
Okay. The smallest possible way to do this.
And I talked to so many people about this okay.
Turn your conventions in the constraints okay.
Sit down and think about the constraints that right now,
if you put an agent on a piece of software in your source control
that it doesn't know it won't be able to get from the source control itself.
That's the first thing that you can absolutely do.
And those constraints are really important.
Encode that one thing that only one person in the organization, the software
it knows because there is definitely one in every org.
100% okay, run that loop once end to end, figure out where it breaks.
And that's the next constraint that you have to go.
You always have to start really small and just fine tune.
You just can't push an agent at your entire source code repository.
And just imagine that things are going to be great.
It will not be okay.
Absolutely will not be. But if you do this right
and in this small, controlled way, what ends up happening?
Is that
AI is going to give you back the work that you've got into the industry to do.
Solving user problems, generating systems for end users
have an architecture and systems design.
I blogged last week saying the words intent is the new architecture.
Both previous sessions in this room guys and then Dana's
was a great reflection of exactly where people are going in that respect.
And I loved seeing both of them because context is the new code.
And Dana started
talking about the fact that intent is how you drive the system going forward.
You can see that a lot of us are starting to come to the same agreement,
the same consensus about what is actually happening here.
So as I told you, I kicked off a swamp image triage
before I started this talk.
Okay?
I started with the command at the top that says triage issue number 518.
It loaded a skill.
It ran a couple of commands.
These are actual swamp commands.
These are our CLI commands which set up the guardrails for the system.
Then what it does is it fetches the details
of the issue, starts to understand the code base.
It's starting to read the operations files.
It's starting to read all of the the context that it actually needs.
It then brings me back a list of summary of findings.
Here's what I found. Here's what's happening.
And then because of that, it can classify it.
And it can basically say, hey, this is a bug.
I have everything I need to write the plan.
Then it builds a very structured plan.
And because it's a very structured plan, it's actually able to give me
a really detailed output of what the plan
is, plus any of the adversarial warnings that are happening in there.
Okay, this is not honestly when I say this is not.
Like super smart.
This is just building guidelines and guardrails.
This is actually what I'm talking about here.
Where is my screen going?
Yeah, there we go.
So it's
really important here that what we're in a situation of doing is
creating this setup, this structure,
this different piece that you need in order to build this factory,
this this system that allows your system to be able to drive forward.
Okay.
And then like for us, we built a in Swamp Club.
So Swamp Club, you can go and have a look at how we've built it.
Because as I said, every single thing here is open source,
all of the issue triage, all of these pieces,
all of these factories are all open source as well.
So for us, we love being able to show this off.
This is like our pride and joy at this moment in time,
because we're having such a great time building the software that we are.
You can find me in the internet at stack 72.
I've written countless blogs over the last four weeks
about how we built this, and it's at stack 72 point dev, and I believe
I have some time for questions.
Thank you.
Do we have any questions?
Right.
There is a super convenient one, Louis, for excellent, Mike.
Thank you.
That was a great talk.
Thanks very much.
Is your what's your bottleneck now?
Is it like because
you're running this on Claude Max or you weren't running it on your laptops?
Is that the bottleneck?
Did you wish you could put this on the cloud or, like.
Wonderful question.
What's our bottleneck?
Bottleneck is deciding what to build.
Okay, I don't run autonomous agents that sit and triage every issue coming in.
That would be madness.
The reason it would be madness is that somebody is going to inject something.
So there's always a human looks at it. Is this worth triaging?
Is this something we care about?
That's the that's our our.
The thinking though is actually deciding what to build.
Because when I can build so fast, I can spin up ten agents at the same time.
But if it's the wrong features
for the users, I'm just going to create this monolithic system that doesn't really
make any sense and has no sort of drive and no consistency going forward.
That's our bottleneck.
Our bottleneck is my thinking, thinking through what is important for our users.
Nice anymore Louis.
You said with your.
You wait for the mic.
That's probably helpful.
You said with the your system, the life cycle review, you know that it's it's
automated until sometimes something gets fled to where the agents can't agree.
And so therefore that's where the human comes in the loop.
What when the human comes in at that point.
How do they gather enough context to be able to decide which way to go?
Because, you know, the agents have been churning so much knowledge that where do I
mean, probably there are different ways depending on the context, but
how do you start to sort of figure out, all right, how do I gain the knowledge?
Wonderful question. Okay.
So we the question is how do we as humans
arbitrate when the agents are actually not able to agree?
So for us, it's like every time we run that command, let that plan,
that adversarial review
that's captured as structured output within our own system, within swamp.
So we can actually use swamp the query and say, hey,
give me the four things that count the green.
Tell me where it can agree.
Because all it is, is just data, right?
Is literally just data where we can actually ask questions
and we can like because it's and it's so easy to understand the difference.
And then we can make the decision.
And if at the end of that we can't make sense of it,
we go right, kill that session, start a new one up,
because we've only lost like ten minutes and there's no issue.
We're not like we're not spending thousands of dollars.
I mean, it's literally a very short period of time
and able to do it so we can spin up as many as we actually need to.
Could you expand a
little bit on your open source model and especially the commercial model?
I'm a big fan.
I completely agree that we are
we are reinventing how open source works, and I like your approach to it.
But what's your commercial model of it?
Okay, so we are in the business of selling software licenses okay.
That is literally it that it's like a red hot model okay.
And the reason it's that way is because people
now care more about supply chain, and they care more about the maintainability
and the drive through that.
So if somebody wants to take our software,
fork it, build it, do whatever they want, go for your life.
It's agPL v3, right? It's the way it works.
You can't build a competing company because that's in our terms of services.
But at the same time, like we are, we are actively working
with a lot of people who want that license,
who want that like that care, that maintainability of the software.
They don't want to have to maintain this themselves.
That's our license model.
One more quick one.
Do we have time?
Thank you.
Thank you so much for this talk.
I think the question that I have.
I'm sure this is still five people in this team right now.
Right.
Is the approach applicable on large scale build
where you have like 100 of microservices and challenger scale and domain expertise?
What a wonderful question.
Is this approach scalable to other people?
Dana said it really well in the last talk.
When you have a guardrails in place, when you have this system in place,
everyone within the org is actually empowered to do the right thing.
We don't believe that we need to scale the company up to hundreds of engineers
to be able to do this right.
What we need is we actually care about people who have architectural vision
on product usability and care to drive the system forward
once they're there, once they know what we're trying to build and do it,
then multiple agents can happen at the same time.
I have five agents running right now, this second on my laptop,
you know what I mean? And that's the way it's going to be.
I truly believe that in the future of software,
in this way, a junior has become really important.
Really important. Okay.
Because right now when juniors commence engineering orgs, they do low level stuff.
They like work on small pieces of code because you can't give them the system.
You can't.
Juniors no can learn architectural constraints of the system.
They don't need to care about the syntax of the code anymore.
Sure, they can read it.
Sure, it's
really important for them to do it, but they actually learn at a faster rate
about the constraints and systems thinking than they've ever done before.
So for us, it's about making sure that we keep that core group of people
who are actually entrenched in making sure that the user feedback is really good.
I created a I hear these questions all the time.
I created a bunch of issues.
These are all questions I've had before where look like things like you
judge six years of work, you threw it away and you're happy with four months.
This is the honeymoon period.
Absolutely, 100%.
Am I going to be like this in four months time?
I'll probably have redesigned the system four times under the hood.
That's just the way this is, just the way the world works.
Maybe I'll even do a bun style rewrite it in rust.
I won't do that.
But yeah, and like, you know, we're learning a bunch.
Anybody who's extra questions, come find me.
I'll be hanging around for the rest of that. Thank you so much.
Enjoy the rest of the conference. It's been a pleasure.
Thank you so much for now.
Thank you.
Thanks very much. Really appreciate it. So next